ILGWU Education Department, Beverly Shulman Papers 5780/106
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Education Department Beverly Shulman Papers
1972-1991
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Shulman, Beverly
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU). Research Dept
5780/106
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Consists of materials on several of the ILGWU's training institutes, seminars, and conferences.
5508335
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Z. Guttendorf, December 10, 2003
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Beverly Shulman was Special Projects Coordinator in the Education Department of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU).
Biographical / Historical
Local union's of the ILGWU established and maintained robust, ambitious educational departments early on in the international's history. As these groups grew in size and scope, the international office sought to coordinate and centralize educational programming for the union's members, culminating in the formation of the Educational Department in 1918.
The department's programming included courses at the Workers' University at the Washington Irving High School in New York City, lectures at Unity Centers and Unity Houses in the northeastern United States, and other events. The educational offerings of the International's Education Department were varied, as had been the education departments of the local unions, and included not only classes in labor studies but also courses in languages, music, and the arts. The ILGWU's 1937 musical "Pins and Needles" exemplified the diversity of the union's programs.
Directors of the Education Department, especially Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, wrote extensively on the ILGWU's programs and worker education in general. Longtime director Gus Tyler not only directed the department, but also served as the ILGWU's on-staff scholar. In later years, the Education Department went beyond collaborating with other education organizations and arranging in-house programs to also supporting post-secondary education for union members and their families.
Scope and Contents
The Education Department records document activities across the entire period of the department's existence, with the bulk of the records covering the 1970s and 1990s. It contains papers from directors of the Education Department: Fannia Cohn, Mark Starr, Gus Tyler, and Kitty Krupat.
The earliest documentation of the department's work is found in the Fannia Cohn papers (5780/049, 5780/049 P); these contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, photographs, and printed material from her work as director of the Educational Department. A microfilm copy of the Fannia Cohn papers held at the New York Public Library (5998 mf) complements the Kheel Center's holdings. Documentation of the work of another longtime leader of the Education Department, Mark Starr, is contained in these records (5780/166, 5780/166 PUBS), as well as in a related collection from Starr on worker education programs (5243).
Documentation of the work of Gus Tyler, who led the merged Education and Political Department after Mark Starr's retirement in 1960, is also contained in the ILGWU records (5780/052, 5780/088, 5780/096). Tyler's papers are complemented by those of Assistant Director Jasper Peyton (5780/086) and Special Projects Coordinator Beverly Shulman (5780/106). These collections contain routine correspondence and memoranda, reports, materials relating to training institutes, seminars, and conferences, and printed material.
The papers of Kitty Krupat, who was serving as Education Director at the time of the ILGWU/ACTWU merger in 1995, constitute the entirety of Education Department records from the 1990s. They include correspondence, memoranda, reports, and financial records relating to the ILGWU's independent and collaborative education projects, including the Worker-Family Education Program, the Joint Union-University Committee on Labor Education, and the Consortium for Worker Education, as well as numerous trainings, conferences, and seminars. Also included in the files are materials from local unions and regional departments of the ILGWU, files on the Internationals' conventions, and reports to the General Executive Board.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/138: ILGWU Education Department, Kitty Krupat Papers 5780/166: ILGWU Education Department Records 5780/166 PUBS: ILGWU Education Department Publications 5780/086: ILGWU Education Department, Jasper Peyton Papers 5780/049: ILGWU Education Department, Fannia Cohn Papers 5780/049 P: ILGWU Education Department, Fannia Cohn Photographs
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Shulman, Beverly.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Educational Dept
5508335
- The Global Factory ILGWU Worker-Family Education Program: An ESL Curriculum, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Expenses, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Correspondence: Incoming and Outgoing, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Bronx Headquarters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Queens Headquarters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Manhattan Headquarters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mayoralty Primary. Leaflet Distribution, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Mayoralty Primary. Endorsement of Mayor Beame, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  August 15 - September 8, 1977
- Mayoralty Primary. Phone Banks, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Citizens Committee for Assumption of Welfare, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Nov. 1977
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Suggestions for Telephone Banks, Local Reports from Local Headquarters., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Mayoralty Primary. Beame. Managers Pictures Taken with Mayor Beame (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hugh Carey Campaign, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Nelson-for-Senate Committee, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Arbitration Seminar, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Oct. 14-16, 1980
- Critical TV Seminar, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Hotels - for Conferences, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Advanced Staff Training Inst., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  March 26 - April 11, 1979
- Advanced Staff Training. Re: ILGWU Training, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Advanced Staff Training. Price Watch Patrol, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Staff Training Institute, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  November 8-21, New York, 1978.
- Staff Training Institute. Correspondence., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Supervisor's Conference, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  June 7-9, 1978.
- Organizers' Conference, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  February 2, 1978.
- Report to the Education Committee of the General Executive Board ILGWU, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  August 20-22, 1979.
- ILGWU National Legislative Conference, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Organizers' Conference. Non Union Forms., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Organizers' Conference. Attendance and Schedule, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Organizers' Conference. Correspondence., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Organizers' Conference. Diplomas., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Organizers' Conference. Materials sent to Ed Schneider., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Organizers' Conference. John DiGirolamo, Weekly Reports., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Advanced Training Institute, Unity House, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  August 1981.
- Advanced Staff Training Inst., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  August 16 - 22, 1981
- Organizers' Conference. Kit Material., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Organizers' Conference. Expenses, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Organizers' Conference. Conference Contracts., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Organizers' Conference. A Study of Voter Attitudes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Organizers' School. Training Institute, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Reservations, Invoices, Checks Received & Paid Out.
- Productivity Seminar. Bank Statements, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- National Legislative Conference, Washington D.C., 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Jan. 29 - Feb. 1, 1978.
- Distribution of Demonstration Materials Country-Wide, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Northeast Dept., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- New York, Queens, Brooklyn, Bronx and Cloak - Out-of-Town, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Eastern Region, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Public Relations. All Submitted Files on Proposed Hiring of PR Firms, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Public Relations. All Bookings. TV, Radio, Newspapers (private interviews), 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Responses to Requests for Literature, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New Scripts, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- ILG Film Strip, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "We are the ILGWU" Booklets, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Harbor Festival, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  July
- Harbor Festival, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  July 4, 1978.
- "Harbor Festival Salute 1980" (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Harbor Festival, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Lane Kirkland.
- Harbor Festival, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Harbor Festival, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  July 4, 1980.